hello and welcome this is otive
inference guest stream
68.1 it's January 23rd
2024 and we're live with Darius parvis
Wayne it's not a podcast I am confused
but it will be fun yes thank you Darius
for coming on feel free to uh introduce
your and the work looking forward to the
presentation and
discussion thank you Daniel yeah it's a
bit it's a bit odd of an experience to
be on this side of the camera and also
for it to be live because I'm used to
having the benefits of uh of sort of
post talk editing although I don't do
very much of that um so I'm Dar P way
and I finished my masters at UCL last
September um I'm currently working at
Royal hallay in a cognitive Neuroscience
lab in my own private work I work in
active inference you may have seen me on
the active inference insights podcast
that I do with the Institute and I've
recently written this paper um called
distrusting the policy how inference
over action shapes our experience of
temporality in flow States and life more
broadly this is kind of a followup from
a paper that was submitted earlier last
year with l s Smith Ry pittia yakob
lowski miles Toof and Carl friston um
and this is a follow-up piece to that
before I start I'm aware that it's a
Punchy title uh and I just want to
clarify that I am not proposing to
explain temporality or the experience of
time entirely because it's an extremely
rich um area of study in which physics
and philosophy and cognitive science
converge and I do not have the time the
effort or the energy to really tackle
all of those problems so it's going to
be rather specific but I'll make clear
where I'm purposefully missing stuff out
okay excellent so
there's kind of a central question
before we even get going which is what
is time and I want to clarify that I'm
not
talking really about so-called objective
time now I know that's itself a
tendentious and tricky claim to make
because of Relativity but we can have a
kind of simple definition given to us
actually by some wonderful researchers
um botai Jabara who have also worked on
active inference accounts of subjective
temporality they Define objective time
as the temporally sequential development
of worldly processes bound relatively to
space and so that will incorporate space
time as a as a concept in physics so
it's spatial in the sense that it
follows spatial laws and it's
indivisible and then it's directional
now this is a little bit more
controversial uh but this ties time to
thermodynamic entropy which goes up in
close stays the same or goes up in close
systems second law of Thermodynamics and
this is the So-Cal thermal time
hypothesis uh Carelli Lee smolen those
are the sort of researchers to go to I
as I said at the beginning there are
obviously diverse accounts of time
especially in phys uh philosophy of time
and the physics of time so three main
contenders are presentism um which
states that only the present exists the
growing block Universe which states that
the past and the present exist and the
future is yet to exist and the
internalism which says that basically
they're all happening now so din uh you
know I believe that there are dinosaurs
is still true um I don't really want to
delve into those if people do um I would
start with the work of someone like John
mtag who was very instrumental in
developing the philosophy of time and of
course there's a lot bit work being done
by K relli uh among others on the
physics of time but what I'm more
interested in today is subjective time
time is
experienced time is a phenomenon in the
sense of being phenomenological
now it seemed to me when I started
writing this paper that everyone had
made the assumption that it flows that
there's a what's called a passage
phenomenology um and I and my account is
predicated on the idea that time flows
that said there is a question mark after
that because turns out there's a fair uh
dose of skepticism about this notion
that time flows even within phenomenal
States so this is called well this could
be ConEd as uh skepticism over passage
phenomenology rather than objective
passage and these are people like
calendar Deng and Miller um so for
example Miller thinks actually it's our
linguistic structures which give us that
impression Deng thinks it it's just
successive temporal events without this
notion of flow or passage um this paper
and this talk I guess can act as a
repost to that again I'm not going to
delve too much into their arguments uh I
would just like to take it at least for
this talk that needs to be treated as
some sort of axium that it's flowing and
then the other thing is that it's thick
and that's a slightly strange adjective
um for me to use here especially for
people who aren't familiar with the
cognitive science of time what does it
mean for temporality to be thick well
that leads us very nicely onto this man
this is Edmund hustle who was the sort
of The Godfather the progenitor of
phenomenology he taught haiger and so
the lineage really starts with him and I
also have to mention William James
because he's very important in this and
William James actually he came up with
the notion of what's called a specious
present and what we could call a thick
present and this is a notion that well
we when we divorce objective time and
subjective time we can cast objective
time as following this kind of linear
sequential uh order so going back to the
botai and Jabara definition we have a
then B then C now hle in his
examinations of subjective experience
and how and
phenomenality realized or recognized or
postulated that the present moment is
not just this uh in this
divisible uh unit of time that can be
separated from the past and the present
rather what makes up the present moment
is itself a constitution of what he call
the Primal impression which we can argue
is this or we're going to talk about
that in a sec this very narrow slice of
nness but also what has just passed and
what is about to become so for example
this is a diagram is an adaptation from
one of H's diagrams because heel is also
a mathematician but as we can see here
let's take this time point B so this is
objective time point B well H we're
saying here is that b is also
constituted by what's called a retention
sorry uh yes a retention of what's just
happened soor we're looking at this line
here so a retention of what just
happened this is a so a retention of
what's happened a but see how here it's
in Brackets it's a part of b and a sort
of what equals a protention what we
could say an active influence is a
prediction of what's about to happen and
so this would be C now C in terms of
objective time hasn't actually happened
yet but the sort of expectations which
are to be fulfilled or not fulfilled um
constitute the experience of B and so do
the uh residual memory in some sense of
a now hus makes it very clear that this
this uh account of temporality is very
different from
uh explicit recollection or expectation
or imagining rather this this uh
structure is the very structure that
defines time Consciousness and so we can
kind of see in some sense how flow
already comes out of this in so far as
protentions are fulfilled or unfulfilled
and therefore become
retentions which
are which recede back in time but also
have this predictive element i. they REM
i. they are prens what's going to happen
and I think to get a little bit more
clarity on this picture it's worth just
discussing this notion of a primal
impression so I think the Primal
impression is for my reading and I
highly recommend this gallager a harvey
paper because I think it's incredibly
Illuminating the Primal impression most
people take as real and as constituting
what gagans or Harvey called the
component of Consciousness that is
narrowly directed towards the now phase
of the object okay so it's a little bit
vague what that
means and actually I think it's more
parsimonious and slightly more elegant
to say that it's an abstraction uh and
this is actually kind of in line with
der's uh reading of hle where he
distinguished the theoretical construct
of the primary impression which is
useful for us in modeling and in an
instrumental way from the actual thing
that appears in phenomen the
phological
Pres um world is always horrible to say
and so my argument here in some way is
that the nowness what now is is in a
sense already anticipated it's it's it's
it's already anticipated because it's
being proted right and that protention
is is in a sense a retention already
because it's projecting into the next
step and it's already predictive for
what's going to come at t+1 so we can
treat the present moment itself as the
result of prediction and then the fact
prediction about the next step and the
fact that that prediction is going to be
uh fulfilled or unfulfilled
now this before I get on to the flow of
time uh I recognize that this is
complicated and it requires uh some
nonlinear ways of thinking I highly
recommend bogar anj's 2023 paper uh
where they actually give a very nice
base graph and active inference account
of this exact way of combining objective
time and subjective time in a hilan way
uh and I think that should clarify
exactly what I mean here again I'm not
actually too interested in deriving a
perfect structure in an active inference
sense a perfect model of hles time I
think that's been done very well by
botar and Jabara and also people like ma
Alber rassin and her team what I'm more
interested is in the flow of time per se
and what's the difference there well
this is the structure of the present as
is as time Consciousness as is I'm more
interested in the fact that time seems
to flow that the present seems to flow
into the past and the future seems to
flow into the present and that itself is
a bit more of a dionic process so that
takes me to the account of time's flow
now whereas the structure of time
Consciousness as I said has been
explored quite comprehensively uh within
the active inference community and
Beyond the notion of time's flow perhaps
because some are skeptical that time
does flow has itself Maybe being touched
upon a little bit less the most famous
or the most um yeah I guess the most
concrete proposal comes from yakob Hoy
and his colleagues and they argue that
the flow of time arises as a system
gives up one hypothesis and settles on a
new one due to its propensity for
distrusting the present so this is a
rather famous 2015 paper called
distrusting the present and the notion
here is that every hypothesis every
state hypothesis I have about my
observation is going to be really good
for that observation but immediately
it's going to become less and less good
because the world changes and so because
I have a higher order expectation that
the world is going to change it's
actually adaptive it's in my best
interest as a free energy minimizing
system to start to distrust this
hypothesis because it's not going to be
capable of explaining the sensations the
observations at t+1 so this is put very
nicely by them as the hierarchical
system settles on this hypothesis which
for them is best at minimizing
prediction error this is continuous
State space stuff so that's totally fine
it needs to begin looking for a new and
better hypothesis and again that's
contingent on this higher order
expectation that the world will change
crucially uh and we will I will explain
this in more depth the mechanism that I
think yakob is proposing here is is
perceptual and attentional uh and we
would cast that as the a matrix um
within pomdp schemes in active inference
and that really casts or encodes the uh
probability distribution of the
likelihood so that is what is the
likelihood of um this state given my
observations No Way Around what is the
likelihood of this observation given my
state the posterior is x given Y and the
idea here is that a um the observation
is uh at time T is yielding precise
precise um precise likelihoods that are
going to govern a hypothesis but because
the attentional spotlight is always
moving around and the world is changing
that observation itself is going to lose
precision and so the new observations
which yield different hypothesis are
going to gain precision and therefore
the system needs to update but I think
most crucially is this notion that it's
perceptual and it's about state or hypo
as he calls it a hypothesis updating a
state hypothesis
updating and crucially for us he also
yakob and his colleagues mention also
the flow uh the speed of the flow of
time so we're now adding another
dimension to this
phenomenology um and I won't read out
the whole thing because that's a bit
dull but basically he's saying that the
faster or the more the more frequently
one up uh one updates one's hypothesis
about the world the faster time seems to
flow so for example we he gives the
example of a war zone well in a war zone
and I think this is totally reasonable
the perceptual hypothesizing has to keep
updating because it's volatile so one
moment I might be perceiving X and the
next moment I might be perceiving y but
that's that the frequency of that is
happening a lot
faster in a different scenario such as
waiting an adult airport the idea would
be that I don't have that I don't expect
the world to be that volatile because
maybe I'm just staring at a wall and so
I don't have to do this perceptual
updating or this hypothesis updating um
as ycob describes it now what's the
problem uh and this is n years old and I
haven't really seen anyone say that
there's a problem um but I thought there
might be a problem and I problem in the
sense is the fact that this account is
fundamentally perceptual and so there
are three T three situations I want to
bring up here and then I'll talk about
how they pertain um to the question at
hand one is what I call St uh static
predictability so this would be
something like staring at a wall for a
prolong period of time so that's our
middle picture here agree that time
would pass rather slowly there now the
second one is so-called Dynamic
predictability now these are my terms
I'm very happy for be able to critique
them but I'm calling this Dynamic
predictability now this would be the
chaps on the right these are those
people who may have played the video
game level and enjoyed it the first time
but for some reason uh some torturous
devil is making them play over that
video game level over and over and over
again
okay so that's Dynamic predictability
I'm not going to talk about how it
pertains right now to the flow of time
and then the other one is flow uh flow
States and again I would Point people in
the direction of the paper that I wrote
with my with my great colleagues last
year on Flow States but this is slightly
different in the sense that the world
the volatility of the world is inferred
there believed to be a sufficient level
of volatility such that I have these uh
narrow action policies these temporally
short action policies and this adaptive
of these fast flows of um motor
responses to the world so it's um so
that's flow stat and you'll get that
canonically in um context such as
surfing rock climbing um and so on so
this is the work of 6s Mahal and others
John thei and hopefully you know we've
contributed something as well
now um let's just very quickly touch on
the speed of time and flow um people uh
this is a ni study by rre and colleagues
in 2021 and they found that the more
flow of participants experience the
faster time passed objectively however
flow did not correlate with duration
estimates now that might seem like kind
of the same thing so how are they
dissociable well I think the easiest way
to think about this is what questions
would you ask to discover these facts
you would ask for the first one did time
how you know how quickly did time pass
subjectively for you and then the second
question would be how long do you think
that took and interestingly in flow we
get this sense that time is speeding up
but we don't actually uh we actually
have quite accurate estimations of
duration so for me this shows that these
phenomenon phenomena are dissociable and
motivates my focus on the subjective
speed of time and flow because there
something going on um this is this is
not particularly incontrovertible um I
don't think because sixense Mahal it it
goes right back to his qualitative work
uh the notion of time dilation has been
present in the literature for a while
but this is actually one of the first
concrete um pieces of experimental work
that has validated that and showed that
inflow time seems to pass faster okay
now I want to go back to this not this
woman um in static predictability
staring at the wall the there are some
nice studies here which basically show
that time does seem to slow down in
these context um so fine we both agree
on that now what's the problem well
remember the the model of distrusting
the present is fundamentally perceptual
um and so you can see here uh yakob and
his colleagues uh account of distrusting
the present in terms of perceptual
attention um and this notion of
attentional spotlighting again um it'll
be much easier for you to read it than
for me to explain it but I think the
critical point here is to take it back
to here according to yob these video
game boys they're going to be in context
where they're getting still volatile
perceptual uh um information in the
sense that I might be playing a video
game where things are changing the whole
time but I've still played it a 100
times so I'm bored and I would postulate
that I think time is going to move
pretty slowly there and in flow States
we've seen that time seems to move
rather quickly but according to this
purely perceptual account there should
be no strong difference between the
sense of time and flow and these
dynamically predictable situations
because because in both of them you
could you could find a situation where
there's the same or even more State
updating to do in dynamically
predictable situations I think an even
stronger example of this I actually put
uh in the paper so there is a paper on
this um where my thoughts are going to
be a little bit more Lucid because
obviously this this is not scripted um
and the example I give there is of the
poor person who has to stare at a screen
with a DOT that constantly changing
color now there's a lot of perceptual
State updating there and let's say it's
randomly changing color so we can't have
an action policy that can pick out the
patterns and say um you know you can
have these extended action policies that
say okay it's going to go red green
yellow red green yellow so it's
constantly changing color now I I was
hard pressed there was no empirical work
that contrasted flow and dynamically
predictable situations uh and so this is
empirical work that I would like to do
and I'll get on to that but I would
still propose just uh heris and
intuitively that time would seem to slow
uh flow rather slowly I think another
issue with this is how we if we go back
to his original example of the war zone
and the do airport even in the context
of St uh static predictability there's
always low-level State updating that's
going on right the world is never static
so even if it's the fact that uh the
paint on the wall is very slowly
cracking or there's a fly that passes in
front of you like the the actual uh the
world itself never changes and howwi
doesn't really give an account of
exactly why or how that can be
incorporated into his model so this made
me think well I don't think the
perceptual hypothesis is necessarily the
most elegant or fits the phenomenology
perfectly and I think it's incred I'm
not I I love yakob um I think it's an
incredible piece of work but I just
think there's a little bit more that
could be
added so this is where I came in with
this notion of distrusting the policy
okay so this is a base graph um this is
actually from L SED Smith's uh 2021 work
uh I won't go too into it although it's
actually not too difficult but basically
what what what is shown here is the fact
that in Act of inference and the
references are there we talk about
action policy selection so policies are
these sequences of action we talk about
these in terms of tree searches so I
might have multiple potential policies
that I could pursue and I basically
calculate expected free energy uh which
we can have as um epistemic gain and
pragmatic gain um if you want I can sort
of talk a little bit more about that but
I don't think we need to get into the
the theory too much I talk about we have
these Tre searches where the agent
evaluates the possible consequences of
these different policies in terms of
expected free energy now they're not
just doing this on a whim as you can see
here at the top of the graph that lar
gives us L and his colleagues because it
was a collaborative paper um the
expected free energy is uh constituted
in part by or or decided upon in part
calculated by the So-Cal C Matrix the C
Matrix are the preferences about the
sensory outcomes that you have so if I
have very highly precise sensory
expectations about how my action is
going to the sensory outcomes of my
action that's going to drive um and it's
in you know and it's in favor with my
generative model that's going to drive
that pragmatic action um indeed the
pragmatic aspect of the expect free
energy formula is the probability of why
the observation given c um there is also
this e Matrix which is habits um we can
take as habits prior as over policies um
and we'll see actually that that comes
in a little bit more in flow but I think
the main idea here is well there's a
couple things one is that an action
policy need not just yield need not just
be isomorphic or map onto just one
observation as you can see here we can
have action policies that stretch deep
into the future as long as we as long as
we presume that the future is
predictable such that um we have we have
an N plus one of the so-called B Matrix
the B Matrix are State transitions so I
might have an action policy where I go
okay I'm going to be in this state then
this state then this state and obviously
this is informed in real time by the
observations I make uh through the a
matrix through the likelihood Matrix but
the point here is is that um the tree
search can like a tree be extended or
narrow okay so that's one thing the
other thing to not here is that every
time I make an action policy or every
time I decide upon an action policy
these things like the E Matrix and the C
Matrix are implicated so we do not just
blindly select an action um this goes
right back to the work of Chris fiff uh
and his colleagues at UCL in the late
90s on uh actually how action happens
and forward modeling but the idea is
that beliefs about the consequence of
our action are fundamental to even doing
action in the first place okay so that's
that's the idea here in terms of the
actual theoretical side of it now what
does that mean in terms of the flow of
time so coming back to the flow of time
so recall that in flow I mentioned it
rather briefly but the idea is that the
world is volatile and although we have a
good grasp of it although we're
occupying or embodying uh what kistin
and others and brunberg and right Val
called a optimal grip we still need to
be aware that the world can change very
quickly so I might slightly have my bow
angle wrong if I'm playing the violin or
the wave might not turn exactly how I
expect it to and what that means is a
deep temporal planning with these deep
trees is precluded in flow now what that
means is if we take five minutes of flow
and we can we can assume that flow does
last that long and there are some nice
empirical studies on that per objective
time unit I'm going to have to be doing
more bouts of planning than I would
let's say in socalled um static static
predictable context and sorry um and
deeply predictable uh and dynamically
predictable contexts so in that case
what what we end up reworking is that
the flow of time is not about
distrusting the present hypothesis about
the sensory data per se because in
dynamically predictable context and in
flow states that might be the same but
rather the iterative speed of belief
updating about the current action policy
now a question that kind of came to mind
mind okay that's that sounds okay but
we've been talking about perception the
whole time and arguably if we're going
to stick to the retention primary
impression and protention scheme we're
going to have to talk about perception
uh and indeed you can see gallago and
Harvey's um sort of uh Point here um
that actually hustle analysis is very
much characterizing perception and
obviously the perception of time itself
is a perception right we're talking
about the phenomenology of time the
phenomenology of Passage time that's a
perceptual act so how are we going to
ground uh planning and policy selection
how we going to fold that into this
picture well it comes right back to what
I said before and it's the fact that
policy selection
includes the deployment or the uh
Precision of certain beliefs in a
generative model including predictions
over preferred Sensations which is uh
encoded in the C Matrix and state
transitions which are encoded in the B
Matrix so if you look on the right side
of the page here
this is actually a base graph from my
paper something I did with Lars and
you'll see here that if um so it's
rather complicated but actually I'll go
through the text first and then we'll
come back to the base graph um again the
idea is actually at least in flow so
maybe it's actually worth looking at it
um what we what flow really entails is a
contextual cue for mental action so what
you see here it's um it's in the mental
state inference box it's you with the
two at the top and the one that's an
action that's triggered by E2 at the top
uh with the superscript and that's a
habit but that's not that's a habit of
driving action but not a physical action
per se what that mental action do uh is
doing is driving aood distribution the a
matrix and so again what that means
really for this for this example or or
for the broader paper um is that mental
action is not limited just to the
selection of policies but also these
Precision way of beliefs about sensory
out comes so what does that mean well it
means that if I do iterative uh policy
updating if I do more iterative policy
updating per objective unit of time then
what I'm also doing is I'm doing more
updating about my preferred sensory uh
expectations I.E my cmatrix is getting
updated more frequently and that's
really the critical point here um so for
example in flow what you're getting is
you're getting this constant uh you can
see here that the The e- Matrix and the
the C Matrix fold into the action policy
because this uh planning would be taken
as to be rather shallow you're going to
have this process iterate more
frequently over a given period of time
now just to clarify for people uh who
might not have any idea what's going on
in this Bas graph as I said the idea
here is that um the mental action is
deploying um it's about deploying
Precision over these uh Precision
beliefs so you have um the likelihood
mapping the Precision of the transition
mapping and the Precision of preferences
note that basically you can't the idea
here is that you can't necessarily
perceive Precision so the way that
that's getting fed back up to the higher
level is through the observations made
at o subscript to superscript one um so
that's actually stated in the italics um
but I think yeah the the point here I'm
very happy to go into this this is sort
of deep parametric modeling which has um
been going on with L's work and Casper's
work Casper hesp and I think it's
wonderful and I'd love to talk more
about it in terms of this though I think
it's a very simple point that these C
matrices whether it's C with the two as
a superscript or see with one as the
superscript which is really going to be
the kind of critical see and flow as the
one with the one superscript because
that's the one which basically drives
the
um sorry no no I'm talking about the
precise beliefs of the sensory
expectations that's the one that's going
to drive the action policy the the U so
to speak um that's just going to get
updated more frequently in flow States
because of the shallow action policies
that flow States in gender so therefore
what's the kind of ultimate uh
conclusion here well my conclusion was
that underline the speed of temporal
temporal flows since beliefs in coding
the C Matrix now this is kind of the
critical point are fundamentally
predictive I.E they prend um and um and
they are also retained over a period of
time why is that it's because my sensory
expectations are going to govern what I
perceive as we know from active
inference because the uh posterior
really is just this negotiation of a
prior expectation and the likelihood
distribution and yet they are also
informed by just past experiences are.
they involve a form of retention because
as you saw with the flow that c Matrix
the sensory uh the sensory exp about the
consequences of my action are
fundamentally Downstream on this
contextual cue
so I think there's a nice way here in
which we can wrap sensory expectations
in coding the C Matrix in the jelan
phenomenology again the really critical
point here is that this is this can be
independent of the pure perceptual
inferences and pureal inferences here
are kind of the combining about prior
beliefs about States um before any
observations the So-Cal D Matrix and a
Precision weighted likelihood
distribution the a matrix so that's
happening at the very top here of the
contextual state
inference in these um dynamically
predictable uh
situations and um in flow States we
might have the same number of pure
perceptual inferences but I would posit
that in flow time seems to move faster
and predictable them predictably Dynamic
situations and the reason I think that
is is because we should be talking about
perceptual uh inference updating about
sens expectations with respect to the C
Matrix uh and not perceptual inference
about the combining of D Matrix and the
a matrix um and again this is because
that uh the frequency with which we
update those beliefs encode in the C
Matrix is contingent on the frequency of
policy planning so just to conclude um
in terms of going forward uh this is
again so just to make it very clear that
it's a pre-print right now this paper I
I'm not claiming that this is the
comprehensive account of uh temporality
or the speed of the flow of time but
it's a suggestion so so um I'd love to
get feedback from people but in terms of
going forward I think this would be an
interesting thing to test whether we
could set up a situation where um we
have one group of you know what your
three groups you have a controlled group
who aren't doing much um a second group
who are playing a video game for the
hundredth time it's predictably uh
dynamically predictable and then flow
States uh which can also be done through
something like a video game and what I
would expect to see just at a very basic
level is that um in flow we could
replicate that finding of time moving
faster subjectively and confirm what I
think is a reasonable intuition that in
these dynamically predictable States
time seems to move slowly or at least
slower relative to flow States
okay that's me
Daniel feel free to far away excellent
all
right great times it flew by I was
paying attention yeah well well it's
very well another part of this I mean I
missed quite a lot out that's part of
the paper the paper's relatively large
is that attention itself is an action uh
and this is often forgotten by people
but attention is a is an action it's a
mental action and that itself will have
its Associated C Matrix so even paying
attention itself would constitute a
mental
action one one note on that and then um
anyone who has a question live chat I'll
read um policy selection under expected
free energy is shaped by pragmatic value
aligning future observations with your
preferences and epistemic value
Information Gain so that's very
interesting that attention as internal
action or covert action could be driven
also by
pragmatic attentive considerations
here's the kind of regime of attention I
expect to be in and also there could be
epistemic or
exploratory regimes of attention that
maybe like reflect us getting distracted
just to gain information even when it
seems to disign us from what we like
expect oursel to be doing right yeah
there are several things that come to
mind there one is that that we do have
these nice um meta attentional models
given by people like Lars and his 2021
paper which includes this deep
parametric modeling so there is this
kind of um what am I paying attention to
how well am I paying attention and you
can have this uh these deep generative
hierarchies where you have attention
over attention the other thing is I've
been I've been this is a slightly
separate Venture but I've been thinking
about the uh the pragmatic value of
attention and I think in some sense um
there's a really nice paper by MIT and
colleagues 2019 where they talk about um
context dependent value driving
attention so if I'm looking let's say
for uh I mean I was talking about
yesterday with juli and kistin on the
podcast if I'm in a crowd and I'm
looking for my friend and he's Ginger
I'm going to up uh up the Precision
waiting of like a template of
gingerness which means that anything
that's kind of Ginger whether it's a cat
or my friend is going to go up and
everything else is going to go
relatively down and this comes back to
original theories of um attention bi's
competition Theory there more than
Duncan but the idea is that that even my
very attentional schema there is being
governed by a high order pragmatic um
the pragmatic gain of finding my
friend and that can be there could be a
lower order element of that which is
that there is value in paying attention
to these things because it it subserves
that higher order uh inference cool all
right I'll go to some questions in the
chat but anyone's welcome to add more
okay Steven CET
asks my question is would you agree that
self-reflective self self-awareness is
necessary for time perception therefore
time requires the
self okay so this is this is an
interesting question um I think in part
it can be answered somewhat by the flow
paper um so in the flow paper it really
does focus on self- modeling and the
idea here is that uh deep temporal
planning in or involves the levels of
the generative hierarchy which are
propositional and cepal and those are
the very levels are associated with a
rich epistemic agent model so this um
self-conception of uh an agent that can
use its knowledge to uh from the past to
inform uh future outcomes and it's it's
future action policies now in flow
because you have these shallow um you
have these shallow decision trees you
actually attenuate that part of the
hierarchy now that means that when
you're in flow people talk about the
kind of self action mer we're not saying
that the self is completely dissolved in
flow States because for example um the
minimal phenomenal self researchers such
as um annel Seth or Felix blankenberg or
yob linowski have grounded that an inter
receptive now it's it's it's I think
it's an open question um there are some
people who think that all experience
involves a fundamental sense of
mindness um so someone like Julian kin
has written a paper on this there are
others who will say that um inter
receptive inference is really at the
heart of the minimal phenomenal self and
if that dissolves then the self model
itself might dissolve now whether you
get time out of that is an interesting
question I would Point people in the
direction of a conversation I had with
Carl where basically we had this there's
this idea that this these different uh
temporal hierarchies are predicated on
the actual dimensions of the mark of
blanket so how nested the mark of
blanket of an organism is because if
you're very far away from your actuators
you have to start making inferences
about what your action is versus what
the world's action is so I think there's
a nice link there between dimensionality
maybe not just physical size but
dimensions in the terms of embedded
markof blankets and time I don't feel
like I'm necessarily qualified to say um
how these two are necessar like
fundamentally connected because I think
there's still an open philosophical uh
and physics related question about the
reality of time
itself awesome
cool you say a little more about trust
and
distrust it's very spicy to call the
paper distrusting the policy because it
feels like the interior dynamics of our
thought should be
like what we can trust so it's kind of a
little bit of a stick in the wheel but
that's kind of fun so where is there
trust and where is their
distrust in what in that kind of a
cognitive
model sure I mean uh this is rift off of
yacob's distrusting the present so I
want to clarify that as a as a master
student you got to try and make some
waves so it was just trying to get
people's heads uh poking up but there is
also the the idea of distrust and I
think you can that as in the form of
precision waiting um to go back to what
yako was talking about in terms of this
um trust as understood by philosophers
we're talking about subpersonal basian
beliefs which include Precision waiting
and it's just that your Precision
waiting over your state hypothesis is
going to be downweighted over time
because there's a higher order belief
that the world is volatile and I think
that higher order belief is really
useful to think about when we're talking
about what trust is in this respect if
you thought that the world was wasn't
going to be volatile such that for
example you're staring at a blank wall
then you could very happily trust that
your hypothesis about that blank wall is
going to be fine in one second two
second 3 second 4 second the idea is
that the the trust comes from this kind
of um perhaps habitual inference that in
this context I am permitted longer spans
of uh deeper trees in this context
however are those deeper trees are
precluded now in some cases that might
be full active inference so there might
be a higher order in a deep parametric
sense a higher order um action policy to
deploy shallow action policies or uh
temporally broad action policies in the
state of flow we argued that this was
habitual but I think the idea here is
that for trust to trust to trust or not
trust in action policy is not that we're
not saying don't trust action right
action is the fundamental curreny in
active inference we're saying you might
want to agents have to be aware of the
degree to which their action is going to
yield them the outcomes they want not
just here and now but also for expected
free energy also for the subsequent
steps awesome yes that clears it up it's
not like policy selection isn't
trustworthy it's that there's a
variable speed at which policies like G
stale that that totally makes sense one
one really um interesting and open topic
is which
phenomena either objective behavioral
computational type phenomena or or
experiential phenomena do we associate
just coarsely more with the a matrix and
load more onto the Sens making component
or more onto the B Matrix more into the
world trans I model or the consequences
of action in the world so like were
there any phenomena that you saw
different
author's approach it like sometimes
discussing that phenomena in the context
of a matrix and sense making other times
more like in this action oriented B
Matrix way honestly I haven't um for I
think I think because deep parametric I
might be missing something but I think
because deep parametric modeling is a
relatively new uh aspect of active
inference a lot of the literature on
this stuff especially in accounting for
phenomenology adopt quite a strict or
pure predictive coding
language so if you read uh this
distrusting the present this yakob and
colleagues paper from
2015 there's no mention of the
difference between the a m uh you know
the uh the D Matrix and the B mat Matrix
right the state this the inferred State
um prior to observation and the state
transitions based on observations which
are contingent on action policies rather
it's just that the prior is informed by
observations and they talk about
precisions of observations where I would
talk about precisions of likelihood
distributions
so I would I I would also I would they
don't touch upon this but I think uh
it's definitely worthwhile me pointing
people in the POS uh direction of this
bogatar and Jabara paper
um it can be a touch confusing because I
think one difficulty that I was having
is it it's hard to it's hard to hold
both objective time and subjective time
in your head at the same time I'm okay
with one and then put then go to the
other um but combining the two is a kind
of amazing feat and they've done a great
job so I would say just answering your
question in terms of where did I see
people providing different emphasis I
would say it's difficult because I
haven't seen that many deep parametric
models of uh of time per se um and so
that's one paper that I would Point
people to but I think it's definitely a
it's definitely a really interesting
area of work about where we really put
all the weight whether it's perceptual
or action but I just didn't think that
perceptual pure perceptual was going to
do it for the flow of time at least not
posited by um yakob and his
team cool well um a few things strike me
from this kind of presentation first how
open and how many ways there are to
address time phenomena in active it
feels more like a toolbox or a mechanic
shop for temporal or dynamical systems
rather than giving us a singular answer
like right off the bat we have discreet
and continuous time now people have made
Arguments for continuous time also
people have made Arguments for discreet
time and suffice to say that we are
using a formalism that straddles both or
can flip between both so there's many
ways to describe it and another example
of like how temporal phenomena can be
brought into play differently is let's
just say we were looking at a 1,000 step
time series we could model that as a
thousand steps of one or steps of 10 or
we could do a nested model so that even
though it's uh one time step model maybe
the slowest level is the whole thousand
time step right so it kind of coar
grains the long time in to kind of
compressing it into a perceptual moment
even if an abstracted perception like is
it possible to perceive the 2000s or is
it possible to perceive you a decade I
thought was a really important part of
this was the fact that we need some kind
of objective order on which we can like
rest our rest our arguments so you see
in the paper and in the talk I really
emphasize the fact that I'm talking per
objective time unit and I'm staking I
know again that's controversial right
but like we just take as a kind of
Miracle of our theory that we have
seconds and minutes and hours if we can
rest what we're talking about in terms
of flows on that kind of um standard
that we can then apply to different
theories then Things become at least
explicable because without that you're
absolutely right it just depends on the
the the level of the hierarchy you're at
or or how deep you've gone into these
time steps um but if you can frame them
within something that we can all agree
on then it becomes relative to that and
I think it becomes uh the science
becomes a lot
simpler cool and also while certainly is
nice and simplifying to take the
chronology or the timeline as an
external given there's also agentically
constructed and then we might be looking
for something like a gamma oscillation
like we're able to distinguish intervals
of time seemingly on the order of
hundreds of milliseconds but not
fractions of milliseconds and there seem
to be some physical reasons like why we
couldn't differentiate two things that
happened within 1 millisecond for
example so it's kind of like that gives
us a bottom up granularity or at least
atomicity for the time process that a
given agent undergoes and for a tree
that might be slower like its duty cycle
might be slower and yet we could still
use the same scale independent formalism
to describe it yeah I mean I I wanted to
make very clear in this that uh I am not
capable of touching upon every element
because this is one of the richest areas
of philosophy and physics and I'm not a
physicist um and to be H I'm not
particularly well versed necessarily in
the philosophy of time um what I wanted
to do in this was stay really faithful
to the
phenomenology so this is informed really
primarily by edman hle um but I think
you're absolutely right I think an
ultimate theory of time if there ever
could be such a
is going to have to integrate or find a
bridge between the so-call objective and
the so-call subjective and I think that
is a qu that's up for grabs I mean
you're absolutely right you can have a
model where it's it's it's all emergent
from um the actual agentic uh being so
it makes me think of sort of Donald
Hoffman I mean Donald Hoffman would just
say that this is a screen you know this
is a this is an interface that's really
useful in biological agents but the
underlying reality has no time um and of
course you have physicists you know this
notion of block time or eternalism that
everything is everything is now every
the past present and future is all real
um again I I this is this is why I think
it's important at least for me and other
researchers when tackling these huge
questions is demarcating exactly what
you're going to be talking about and uh
I don't have the skill or the Acumen or
the time if you pardon the pun to do the
the Stein and the the call relli sorry
chaps I I would have written a shorter
letter if I had different
time quite still
counter I'll ask a question from live
chat Sor is
asks can the agent perceive time as the
amount of parallel actions taken between
events of
attention I I'll give a first thought on
that
y with what Chris field shared in the
physics as information processing we
talked a lot about the measurement and
the preparation cycle and so in active
inference at each time step sometimes
we're just talking about like a vertical
slice and there's an observation coming
in and a hidden State inference it's all
described kind of synchronously in the
moment whereas in the quantum framework
there's a bit more of a two stroke phase
to the measurement which is that it's
prepared and then measured and so if the
external
oscillator let's just say again give
give us seconds for now if it's going at
1 second and an agent were preparing and
measuring 10 times a second well then
nine of those 10 would kind of come back
empty like the nine sequential
measurements and proposal preparations
and me measurements that didn't have any
change would be kind of like in a
Timeless or same time moment they all
would have like pinged the clock and
gotten the same state back um and then
conversely an agent could use the rates
and the type of change or
interaction with the
environment as a proxy of change and the
example I think of there is like
honeybees using the optic flow as part
of their distance calculations and
people have shown like if you have the
honeybee move through a tunnel with very
rapid black and white alternation it
overestimates the distance it flows
right and then if you have it in large
contiguous color blocks it
underestimates the distance it flows so
it's using the rates of optic flow
change frame differencing which is also
the origins of predicted processing
using those kinds of external
oscillations or changes is as part of
its embodied time
perception right yeah I the way I would
approach this is exactly what you said
which is when we when we build a base
graph something that s of became very
clear to me is that we we are taking
time we are slicing time which is
already which is a detriment because I'm
trying to talk about dionic time whilst
slicing my model and I think this really
does just exhibit sometimes the Discord
that we have between our modeling and
the actual reality so it's it's an
inherent weakness or an inherent
limitation of our instruments what I
will say is I think it's interesting to
talk about uh parallel processing rather
than serial processing here because as I
keep trying to make clear this
generative hierarchy is rather deep and
so I think for example you know I
mentioned when one stares at a
wall there's always some State updating
right the the game is never the the game
has never paused and so I think there's
actually an interesting follow-up
question here which is if we stack all
of these regimes of attention up and we
have rapid flows in all of them right
does that lead to an even more
pronounced sense that time is Flowing
faster in the way that maybe now we can
have this nice hierarchy of what I could
predict uh stable predict uh stably
predictive d uh situations dynamically
predictive situ and flow where the
difference really is the actual number
of attentional regimes in which you're
seeing updates because I don't there is
bear in mind that to update the C Matrix
you have to know where you are in the
first place you have to be able to do
the state uh updating it's just that for
me that was insufficient to explain the
phenomena at hand but if you can now
start taking that kind of base graph
that I showed uh where is
it you know if we can take this Bay
graph
and in principle apply it up and down
the generative hierarchy well if these
narrow um flows are are happening all
the way up and down maybe there's an
interesting thing there that this is
really you know the the the top end of
Passage phenomenology and rather and if
these are really protracted at every
level right right down to the very
lowest markof blanket of our system and
right up to the move rather slowly so I
think there's some interesting ideas
there um and I think it it feeds into
this notion that we we occupy or embody
embedded markof blankets that go beyond
us and in many ways go kind of beneath
us I mean it depends on where you cast
your identity but yeah I think the
parallel thing here is is really
interesting but for instrumental
scientific reasons it was just a lot
easier for me to like and philosophical
reasons just to take one slice at one
level of the hierarchy although this
does have some
parametrization cool okay so looking at
the figure from your paper yeah so this
one but but by the way this one's from
the first flow
paper okay I think this one yeah so this
one's from the first flow paper um I'm
not sure I need to check I'm not sure it
makes an appearance in the second one
but it's it it's it's that's where it
comes from okay so for any parameter
that you know or love on this this
diagram yeah what what would you say is
like a prompt or a cue that might help
us understand or come even to an
intuitive felt sense sure pick pick
anyone because I think that's like super
interesting and it's all awesome to look
at this as like the compilation
instructions for a base graph which is
in one sense what it is technically
however also as we're talking about our
own minds and experiences here it's like
super fun and definitely of interest to
tap into whichever letter and then let's
see if we can kind of go from there yeah
so as a sort of just forewarning um this
was like yeah as I said constructed with
Lars I mean L's really LED on this
project I should give him a lot of
credit um and so I also don't want to
butcher his work because I know he's
really into this sort of deep parametric
modeling that he learned from KL but you
it's my paper so I have a good idea
what's going on here um I think I could
do an okay job of actually explaining
what's going on more generally um which
is the idea here is that let's just
start right at the top at the top is not
particularly it shouldn't be too
confusing which is that basically you're
just inferring the state that you're
in right so what do you mean by state so
the hidden state right so I'm inferring
um so this um given this observation of
you know whatever has hit your receptors
I believe with some high Precision that
I in a uh you know I'm about to start a
violin concerto okay let's go with the
violin violin kerto situation and just
so I'm about to start paying my violin
now what does that mean well that feeds
into this e Matrix um this e with the
two as the superscript and so what we're
saying here is is that that very State
inference acts as a contextual cue for
the deployment of this action you uh
with the superscript two and subscript
one so really this is all basically
driven by this e Matrix e with the two
superscript now what does that look like
well what's really important here is
this s with the superscript two and
subscript
two because what they what we're saying
here is is that we we're we're we're
posing a mental action and the mental
action is to increase per decision over
the likelihood mapping the trans so the
likelihood mapping is here the
transition mapping and the uh position
of preferences so what we're saying here
is that this action is basically it it
in some sense it this is its kind of
preferred State um now the only issue as
I said is we can't observe Precision
what we can observe are the outcomes of
our action so what we're now saying here
is that basically this observation here
through this likelihood Matrix will feed
back up the hierarchy and inform the
mental state inference here oh you've
you've yes you've succeeded in
increasing
precision and the reason for that is as
you know if we get increased Precision
over the C Matrix and the B Matrix we
are driven by pragmatic action at least
according to the expected free energy
formula so that's kind of what's going
on here um note to is there anything
else that's kind of
relevant
um yeah I mean you so you got to bear in
mind that like so again this is uh
mental action but these are the these
are the physical
actions so these are the actual playing
of the
violin right and they're going to
contribute to this observation but this
obs is really in terms of mental state
inference doing the job of saying you've
done a good job at increasing Precision
over your sensory expectations the
likelihood Matrix and transition um
mappings let let me um try to try to
Echo this yeah we're in the violin
setting so at the purple top layer
there's two contexts there's the
presentation in the
auditorium that's the real thing and
then there's the practice at home so
there's two contextual States and and
90% of the time you're at home so that's
your prior but then sensory evidence
suggests that you're in the auditorium
so that's the context um the blue layer
is the action policies like the angle
and the motor um activity of the arm and
the Hand of the violinist this is this
is yes this is the physical actions yeah
yeah and the Orange is the regime of
attention of the musician now right what
they expect in terms of
recital from sheet music yeah is that
pragmatic value is playing like the most
amazing and Transcendent version of the
sheet music as written so of course the
map is not the territory however
pragmatic value is defined as hitting
those notes at the right order in the
right time so it's not like an epistemic
exploratory um place so now um how how
do we think about how those motor
movements are
skillfully done which can include not
just deafness but also planning like um
a wind player has to plan their
breathing and there's other things and
planning the um motions all kinds of
things and so um your kind of contention
with the flow state is that in a
skilled um cant mahol setting y where
there's Precision like yeah I am good at
skiing I am good at violin personally
not but I'm just saying um yeah yeah
yeah when confirmatory evidence is
coming
in then that
enables a
shorter time Horizon of planning so A
vastly reduced cognitive overhead but
relying on tacit and implicit heris
discs that enable
um professional outcomes to
arise in that flow State even if
somebody looking from the outside
thought oh wow they must have really
planned that yes however it wasn't
really planned and then we kind of have
the orange level the regime of attention
meeting in the middle and mediating this
like cultural contextual understanding
top down with the body bottom up um
sensory
component yeah so that's that's that's
basically it um there there's plenty of
things to point out there one is um I
had this idea that these observations
that you're making sort of in real time
are actually basically Loop Round into
this contextual State inference so at
time n plus one it actually kind of
feeds it into a conversation about time
what I've actually just observed so the
very sound that has come out of my
violin itself is feeding
the contextual State inference which
itself feeds another habitual action to
cast Precision over sensory expectations
about the next thing that I'm going to
play and then that Cycles so we're
basically saying that although the
actual um action policy the actual
selection of the actual policy here at
C1 is pure active
inference the mental action that drives
High Precision over it is Habitual and
that itself is driven in this recursive
way so that's one thing yeah the other
thing is is about this kind of shallow
temporal planning that's exactly right
that's exactly what we propos the reason
for this and this was actually raised by
yakob har that's I'm very grateful for
his observation here and this is
actually mentioned in his um 2022 self-
evidencing paper is that um the like
it's not the case that when I play my
violin skillfully I can say okay I know
I have it's not the case I believe that
everything I do is going to be highly
predictable for 3 or four minutes cuz
that would afford deep temporal planning
rather as I said there are these
volatilities in the environment that I
always need to be adjusting myself to
right I need to be conforming myself to
I need to be able to exploit those
affordances so flow states are not just
one extended action policy which is
super rigid rather it's it's kind of
because because each state uh inference
ex itself acts as a contextual cue over
certain sensory expectations we have
this kind of uh fractal nature where you
might have like the first state well
might be fractal but it's like a tree
you have the first a inference and then
the and then you have these bations such
that sure everything is um constrained
within the piece that you're actually
playing but it's not going to be the
same piece every single time now what we
do say is is that if I have an
observation for example if my string
suddenly breaks what happens is this
with this Bas graph is it it basically
collapses and and the reason for that is
is that that lower level perceptual
State inference which feeds into the
context I'm in is no longer a sufficient
context to trigger the habitual mental
action so it's not just the case that
you can be inlow in any context right
that's really important um there's a set
of uh contexts which are going to
license this mental action and that's
very nice to explain within active
inference as just hashing uh action
policies as habits so the more you do
them uh the more they just get cached
and the sort of um more precise that is
as a KNE Matrix so that also allows us
to talk about cognitive effort in line
with Thomas PA's 2023 paper about sort
of it being divers uh you know effort
being Divergence from PRI uh prior over
policies but yeah I mean the fundamental
Point here is that flow is a weird one
because everything is like very
predictable within its ra within its
action policy regime but that's
it the skill really is being able to
have like a diverse or fractal uh
structure where you can go to different
nodes and they all link together through
habits
basically awesome okay few fun questions
in the chat about Precision get your
Precision goggles on I hope you're
confident yeah okay Dave writes yeah
quote we can't observe our precision
he says this assertion seems to need
clarification or qualification
eventually our precisions have profound
effects on our actions and anxieties
they must need attention somehow and in
fact affective active
inference have posited that there's
something like the observation of a
variance parameter and that that's
associated with anxiety and veilance by
hesp at all so which variances do we
imagine are introspective and
why
so that's a good question
um at least in the way that this I I
don't think to be honest it makes a
dramatic difference whether you have
another level within this base graph
which has the observation of
precision our idea here is that just
because things are happening very
quickly it it might just be parsimonious
to invoke that the evidence for that
Precision waiting comes from the
observations so that's that kind of oh
um with a two as a subscript and one as
a superscript um but no I mean I I'm not
going to I'm not going to die on this on
this hill uh because also I don't think
it makes a massive difference um I might
I would be personally inclined if he was
here to pass this one off to
lar um because that was the way he
explained it to me and I'm not trying to
exculpate myself but recall that this
paper is a six or five auor
collaboration so it's not all me but
that's the way that I would say I would
say that there's no harm in saying that
you can observe your preferences oh
sorry you're Precision waiting but in
some sense we're treating this extra
receptively um and so yeah this this
would this seems to work um in a way
that doesn't need to invoke
a another layer to the
hierarchy great that's not a hill to die
on that's our research
field yeah exactly but but seriously it
it's a great question by Dave and those
are the questions that we could
imagine real studies to ask or
address yes so it's it's those are the
great questions okay yeah I mean the
other thing I would say here is
something that's become quite obvious to
me again I mean I'm not the expert on
this you might want to ask Thomas par
but something that's become very obvious
to me is that there's a difference we
got to make a difference between
attention precision and precision
waiting um and I think there's often
times in the community a conflation of
those
three and so when we saying okay we need
to pay attention to these certain things
well atten in the a
matrix um which is a certain type of
precision but we have other precisions
in mental state in mental inference
including these C matrices B matrices e
matrices and d matricies and they do not
all map onto attention so this idea that
Precision waiting is
attention which is kind of an okay
heuristic it's not really what's going
on yes the terms not not to make like
too general of a statement here but the
terms that refer more generally to
statistic like State belief variance
attention Precision confidence usually
without more qualification they're too
vague like just saying something as a
prior are we talking about D in the
purple D2 D1 are we talking about B
playing the role as the prior for a
future time step so um like they are
course grings their fingers pointing at
moons and then there's the movement of
the solar system and there's a lot of
pointing and gesturing
and also thankfully rapid accelerations
of our understanding and our tool
environment to help like move this model
for example into an executable format or
to use verbal descriptions of it and
there's some really exciting and fun
things like even just pasting this image
or uploading the paper into a language
model can give some fun and different
insights now it may take an expert to
then evaluate whether what it says is
accurate or not however that's a super
promising Avenue for like developing
context and metaphors or examples for
looking at
this yeah I mean I need to add that like
I have I I really do not I'm not
treating this as like a way to have a go
at philosophers because my background is
in philosophy and cognitive science so
this emphasis on the computational model
in many ways actually owes a lot to Carl
because when I presented this flow paper
for the first time in his group he was
like well it's sounds sort of
philosophically narration good but kind
of the emphasis now is on like can you
put this into M lab can you build
something from it um that said I mean as
I said this is informed fundament this
paper at least was informed
fundamentally by lived experience and
phenomenology so I guess what I'm trying
to become a part of is the so-called um
generative passage uh which is finding a
way to get from phenomenology to basian
mechanics and hopefully this is one way
but I don't I don't I don't I don't
propose that I'm reducing the rich
phenomenology of lived experience to
these basium mechanics um because I
think that would be slightly
humoristic because no one
knows yeah it's not even just
approaching it from both sides I don't
think there's only two sides to this
yeah there is though this just like you
said grounding in the felt experience
and the phenomenology the the ontology
and the
practices of
philosophy and also
formalism and wanting to touch grass but
touch Matt lab as it were yeah and then
that kind of strange looping when our
felt
experience H has a reference of a
cognitive map and model right and that
kind of special a yeah yeah there's a
tripartite structure here which is one
the basum mechanics two the uh the model
and three the phenomenon the target
phenomenon and I think again this is
actually really uh become apparent to me
after speaking to Julian yesterday
Julian kin that one has to be careful to
not fall into the tendency to conflate
them or reduce one to the other as you
say uh the map is not the territory is a
really crucial component of all of this
I mean I can provide a generative model
I can speak about C
matrices I I I I really want to clarify
do not mean that in a reductive sense
that the flow of time is a c you is the
updating of the C Matrix what the actual
binding the relation is there I don't
know
um whether it's emergent strongly
emergent weakly emergent epiphenomenal
is ontologically reductive it is is is a
good
question
um but it's an open question I don't
think we should just take for granted
that they are one and the same thing
that we're making an identiy
claimer yeah of course many
interpretations and we we welcome them I
see this as like a a boundary artifact
or a design artifact that brings us to
the point of ju's deposition of all of
those schools of thought that you just
mentioned in more and then it's like
through the bottleneck
together maybe the distribution of
beliefs on the other side is the same
maybe it's different right but we came
together we synchronized our generative
models and then we get to continue the
discussion like
from a point of contact or alignment
otherwise different assertions might be
made that don't even have the same
underlying axiomatic set or refer or
inclusion Criterion at which point you
might as well have one person saying
well I designed a pickup truck and
someone else is arguing about whether my
red is your red and someone else talking
about ecology it's like it would be like
blending up pages of a library and not
it's very yeah it's very important to to
keep a philosophical eye on on the
theories that are emerging and and to be
honest Daniel I mean it's credit to you
I think as a younger person entering
into active inference you guys have all
done a very good job at not making us
subscribe to one philosophical position
um one ontological EP epistemological
position I mean people have their own I
for one I'm personally happy to leave it
open I mean I say that before doing my
PhD I'm sure after my PhD I'll be an
acolyte of some of some way of thinking
but I think this is the exciting thing
about active inference and hopefully
that enthusiasm comes across in the
podcast which is like it kind of works
whether you're a reductionist and an
epip phenomenalist like it's just maths
and statistics and it it's it's
informative for philosophical
conversations and so philosophical
conversations are informative to the
maass and statistics and framing it but
it doesn't it doesn't constrain you like
um maybe having a super radical and
activist cognition account might
constrain you or being a pure
computation list might constrain you so
so uh credit to everyone credit to
credit to car credit to you no it's it's
good thank you that thank you it's
awesome and it makes me wonder there's
so many ways to go from there but how
much of this is active inference itself
if anything could even be itself and how
much is merely optimal grasp of
formalism and just seeing that whatever
you write on the floor the table or the
page any equation category Theory
dynamical systems statistics like any
anything is the diving board that you
have to jump into the pool with for
phenomenology and so what's the point of
comparing diving boards only if it's
about dive you'll notice I didn't even
mention active inference I mean like I
mean one because I'm we're here with the
Institute it would be a bit silly to
waste time explaining what the free
energy principle
is um I mean from my perspective the way
that I talk about it is well I'll take
the free energy principle is just
unfalsifiable true as a principle of
physics it's like it doesn't really get
more fundamental than the free energy
principle where it really gets
interesting is the fact that if I am to
be considered the same agent or same
organism from time one to time two then
I need to be abiding by the free energy
principle now the real question is how
am I doing that and predictive
processing or PP seems give a really
nice weigh in but I kind of just take it
that like I'm doing some form of active
inference all the time and like from
that I let it take me where it takes me
whether I stick purely to a
philosophical account or whether I stick
to a more computational account like
none of my commitments there are
negating my ultimate commitment to my uh
you know the the everpresent reduction
of variational free
energy so it's a nice building block but
as you say I think uh the lovely thing
about it is it can lead you in different
Direction sure it might be I don't want
to say that it's just an Open Season
people have their commitments so if
you're a predictive coding guy you have
your commitments if you're a variational
message passing guy you have a
commitments for me I'm not I hav I
really don't have any skin in the game
at that level because I've been in this
game for a year so um I'm happy to I'm
happy to see where things go and and and
just yeah see how and for me it's really
important that it maps on in some way to
the phenomenology if you're talking
about something that clearly like just
from Pure analysis of my own experience
is not the
case well then then that's
problematic interesting again I I love
this topic and there's many things we
can continue on and it makes me think
about how coming from an animal behavior
and genetics
background where firsters experience was
either implicitly or explicit all of the
phenomenology
feels special to bring in kind of like
the leavening of the bread a little bit
because the animal behavior perspective
is like everything but this right even
the orange layer here would be kind of
like a a proposal for a cognitive
analysis but only to get a better handle
on the
blue never because there was something
intrinsically like meaningful or
experiential it would be just too
speculative and a field so it's just
interesting to come from the orange
layer and descend into the blue and get
into the nitty-gritty with the motor
reflexes and the iades and the way that
philosophers get into these embodied
phenomena and then also from the
embodied in the behavioral scientist
side to come up into be like yeah
actually we can't s side step some of
these philosophical questions it does
matter how these different systems
perceive and engage with time
yeah I mean I think it's important to
bear in mind that um the behaviorists
for example never they never they never
actually excluded in terms of
ontology uh in their case
representational States they just said
that like they're uninteresting to
science because they're unobservable so
like an animal someone studying ANS as
you do or bees they're behaviorists but
that actually doesn't that doesn't um
that doesn't commit them to saying
anything about the representational
capacities of a be or an ant
um but yes I mean these philosophical
questions are interesting I'm personally
happy to start at the insights that
people like Merlo Ponte or hle or
someone like Julian have derived from
these very precise I mean phenomenology
is not just like a random science it's
not woohoo like it's it's it's codified
and
categorical and I'm happy to start with
that and then when I find something like
uh the that
clearly violates what at least seems to
be pretty obvious in my experience now
to go to your experience would require
some philosophically slightly uh
Troublesome inferences because you know
you could be a philosophical zombie and
I'm not zombies um but at least for my
experience you know when people you know
people get very angry about uh
Illusionist about Consciousness not
realizing that they're not actually
Illusionist about Consciousness they're
illus Illusionist about phenomenal
States or phenomenal qualities but if
you for example you were an Illusionist
about Consciousness wholesale well I
just I I can't start there with you
because you're saying something that is
just so clearly wrong so again I'm not
going for Daniel denner or Keith franker
because I know they actually don't say
that but for me it's a decent starting
point to say well I have very intimate
uh knowledge of that which is happening
subjectively and let me see how close I
can get there with computational schema
whilst not losing the phenomenology I
think that's the important thing and
then I think where you end up
emphasizing is just like what your
interests are right like I'm
fundamentally a philosophy guy I'm not a
computationalist by training as you can
see probably from my explanation of this
graph um so I've been really lucky right
I've been really lucky to work with
people like lar and Carl who have kind
of helped me and I think it's really
really useful but again I'm not going to
lose sight of lived
experience um and I don't think anyone
personally I don't think anyone should
but it's difficult as as you say when
you're studying animal behavior
because well that's that seems like a
stronger inference to make because maybe
they don't have public language to say
what it's like to be an ant or a beast
to paraphrase Thomas
nle well very fun um
what are your next steps or
directions so yeah so this is up on the
preprint as I said I want feedback I
want people to get angry and attack me
uh orbe it in the spirit of scientific
consilience um so I'm I very much
encourage
feedback I think um I'm hoping to get
some more formal reviews from some
people and then we'll try and get this
out there somewhere I don't know quite
where I'm working on some other things
um which I'm sure I can speak about I'm
working on a paper about self- modeling
in Tourette with liby s which is super
exciting um so that's coming together
I'm working I'm at the very early stages
of working on something about extended
mind uh with Ma and others so that
should be really fun and the
podcast um we've been putting in loads
of work on the podcast so we have Chris
rff which is super exciting just a sort
of Pioneer in Psychology uh Julian kin
as I mentioned Alex or Robia in a
wonderful conversation about biometics
and cybernetics and I learned loads and
Lance the
Costa and that was the one where I was
telling you before we went on live there
was a lot of maths learning so to be
honest Daniel I'm just learning um and
I'm applying for phds and hopefully that
will kick off either later this year or
or the new year but I'm not going anyway
I'll put it that
way awesome very fun yeah very epistemic
very chill so very chill yeah a lot of
good comments in the live chat you can
review so thank you um everyone in the
live chat thank you Darius and thank you
everyone see
youall thank you thank
bye
that